A Finding Aid to the Mary K. McGuigan and John F. McGuigan Jr. artists' letters collection, 1794-1938, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
- Mary K. McGuigan and John F. McGuigan Jr. Artists' Letters Collection, 1794-1938; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.6 Linear feet Boxes 1-3
  - Harding, Chester, circa 1846-1865; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8-11)
    Chester Harding, Springfield, Massachusetts, 22 December 1864, to his daughter-in-law Julia Norton Delano Harding, Detroit, regarding his wedding gift of money, as well as Frank's looking into the disposal of his property in Detroit.
    Chester Harding, Springfield, Massachusetts, 15 April 1865, to his daughter-in-law Julia Norton Delano Harding, Detroit, regarding a blunder that cost Frank his job, the poor prospects for Frank's starting a new business in Detroit, and the assassination of Abraham Lincoln.
    Chester Harding, St. Louis, 11 October [1865], to his daughter-in-law Julia Norton Delano Harding, Detroit, regarding the hot weather in St. Louis, his intention to stay until Christmas, and his desire to paint several portraits to keep busy.
    Chester Harding, manuscript fragment, comprising parts No. 2, 3 and 4 of his memoir, A Sketch of Chester Harding, Artist, Drawn by His Own Hand, later edited by his daughter Margaret Eliot Harding White (1823-1903), and published in Cambridge, Massachusetts, by John Wilson in 1866. This is the only known portion of this manuscript.
  - Hassam, Childe, 1904; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Childe Hassam, New York, 24 March 1904, to the novelist and playwright Louis Evan Shipman (1869-1933), Cornish, New Hampshire, regarding payment for a painting and an invitation to visit. Includes envelope.
  - Healy, George Peter Alexander, 1889; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Paris, 18 January 1889, to Miss Wright. Healy writes either to a close acquaintance or patron after receiving some family photographs. Describes works in his studio: full-length portraits of Archbishop Rearden of San Francisco and General Winslow, and a half-length portrait of Monsieur Barbedienne. For the Paris Salon he intends to send full-length portraits of Cardinal Archbishop James Gibbons of Baltimore and Abraham Dreyfus. For the Universal Exposition at Paris he intends to send a half-length portrait of the Earl of Lytton, former English Ambassador to France, and a full-length painting of a fourteen-year-old girl playing the violin.
  - Hollingsworth, George, circa 1870s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
    George Hollingsworth (1813-1882), carte de visite of the Massachusetts painter.
  - Hunt, William Morris, 1877; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Boston, 22 November 1877, to John Ferguson Weir, New Haven."My time is already more than taken up in trying to learn how to paint and as I can get no information on the subject from lectures. I do not think I could assist others by lecturing. The world is full of people who lecture on art and I will not interfere with them."
  - Huntington, Anna Vaughn Hyatt, circa 1880s, circa 1933; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Anna Vaughn Hyatt Huntington (1876-1973) candid oval photographic portrait, circa 1933. Christmas gift from Harriet Randolph Hyatt (1868-1960) [Mrs. Alfred G. Mayor], sister of Anna Hyatt Huntington, noted painter, and former pupil of Dennis Miller Bunker, 12 December 1933, to Anna Bemis Stearns (1867-1949). Mrs. Mayor also included a sketchbook portrait of Anna Bemis signed "H. R. H." [Harriet Randolph Hyatt], and a note that says "I thought you might like to own this sketch of other days I found in an old sketchbook. I hear from Anna [Huntington] that she…"
  - Huntington, Daniel, 1862; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
    New York, 11 April 1862, to Alexander Hay Ritchie (1822-95, engraver and genre and figure painter), New York. Huntington writes to A. W. [sic] Ritchie, 422 Broadway, that he is suffering from the flu and is unavailable for Ritchie to pick up the photograph of his (Huntington's) uncle that Ritchie will engrave; but he will arrange the matter later, including the size of the plate, when he is better. "I think I shall keep a safe distance from the Exhib. on Varnishing Day."
    Daniel Huntington (1816-1906), New York, "Wednesday 20th," to Richard William Hubbard (1816-1888). "The Sketch Club are to meet with me on Friday Evening. I shall be happy if you can be with us."
  - Inman, Henry, 1834; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Henry Inman, New York, 30 January 1834, to Prosper Montgomery Wetmore (1798-1876), Albany, President of the American Art Union. Regarding his quest to secure the commission to paint one of the panels for the Capitol Rotunda in Washington, DC, as well as a favorable mention of his talent by John Quincy Adams in the New York Mirror. Includes an engraved portrait of Inman.
  - Inness, George, 1884, 1887; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19)
    George Inness (1825-1894), Milton, New Jersey, 25 May 1884, to Laura Maude Wachschlager. Re: Waschlager was a young autograph collector.
    George Inness, corrected proof, approved and signed for his entry in Men of the Time: A Dictionary of Contemporaries, containing Biographical Notices of Eminent Characters of Both Sexes, 1887, published by George Routledge, London, 1887.
  - Jones, Hugh Bolton, 1888; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)
    New York, 26 March 1888, to George Frederick Munn (1851-1907, naturalist painter). Jones responds to Munn's request for photographs of pond lily leaves, mentions Jones's picture owned by Mr. Halstead, and apprises Munn of the current addresses of the painters Edwin Howland Blashfield (1849-1936), Thomas Hovenden (1840-95), and William Lamb Picknell (1853-97).
  - Jones, Thomas Dow, circa 1870s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Thomas Dow Jones (1811-1881), sculptor, cabinet card portrait of the artist, inscribed by him "T. D. Jones/Sculptor."
  - Kensett, John Frederick, circa 1869; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22)
    John Frederick Kensett, Monday, 20 December [ca. 1869], to Richard William Hubbard (1816-18), artist.
    New York, 1 October 1865, to William A. Baker, Auburn, New York. Kensett responds to Baker's request for an autograph and informs him he has just returned to the city.
  - Knight, Louis Ashton, circa 1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Louis Ashton Knight (1873-1938), press photograph by Bonney, "'Pont Louis Ashton Knight'…Bridge named after well-known American painter." Shows Knight painting on the bridge.
  - Lang, Louis, 1872; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 24)
    New York, The Institution for the Savings of Merchants' Clerks, bank check, 22 April 1872, for $35, payable to Mrs. Dillor or Bearer.
  - Leslie, Charles Robert, 1832; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Charles Robert Leslie (1794-1859), [London, 21 April 1832], to Abraham Cooper (1787-1868), English painter. Re: "I shall feel obliged if you will let me know when Mr. Marshall's creditors meet and whether or not you intend to be present."
  - Lossing, Benson J., 1873; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Benson J. Lossing, eminent historian and art historian, Dover Plains, New York, 2 December 1873, to Morven M. Jones (1815-1886), Utica, New York, attorney, autograph collector, and victim of one of the most scandalous political trials of the Civil War. Regarding the publication of his historical documents.
  - Low, Will Hicok, 1895; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Giverny, France, 25 September 1895, to Mrs. S. C. Blodget, East Greenwich, Rhode Island. Writing from the prominent artists' colony and home to Monet, Low responds to Mrs. Blodget that he does not possess any photographs of his works but that copies can be procured by contacting William Kurtz, 6 E. 23rd St., New York.
    Giverny, France, 25 September 1895, to William Kurtz (1833-1904, artist and photographer), New York. Low authorizes Kurtz to make copies of photographs of any of his paintings for Mrs. S. C. Blodget, of East Greenwich, Rhode Island, with the exception of the Diploma Design for the Columbian Exposition. Included with this letter are two carte-de-visite photographs of unidentified women by W. Kurtz, presumably Mrs. Blodget and her daughter.
  - MacMonnies, Frederick William, 1907; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Frederick William MacMonnies (1863-1937), Giverny, France, 28 March 1907, to Miss Jones. Re: some photographs to be sent.
  - Mayer, Francis Blackwell, circa 1880s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 29)
    Francis Blackwell Mayer (1827-1899), two cabinet cards, "John E. McCusker posing as Col. Steward for the Artist Frank Mayer, in his Picture of the Burning of the Peggy Stewart-now at the State House, Annapolis, Maryland." Photographic studies for Mayer's The Burning of the Peggy Stewart during the Annapolis Tea Party in 1774 (1886), Maryland State House.
  - Mills, Clark, 1870; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 30)
    [Clark Mills] Bank Check for $600 from the National Lincoln Monument Association, Washington, DC, 30 March 1870, paid to "self" and signed by sculptor Clark Mills (1810-1883).
  - Morse, Samuel F. B., 1826; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 31)
    Autograph letter signed "Sam'l F. B. Morse." Two pages. New York, 30 March 1826. Addressed to Charles R. Leslie, Esq., in London.
  - Myer, Marie Shields, 1912; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Marie Shields Myer, 1 June 1912. Invitation from the New York School of Applied Design for Women for an exhibition of Myer's works on view from June through August 1912.
  - Nast, Thomas, 1866; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 33)
    Thomas Nast, Catskill, 29 July 1866, to the Albany architect John B. Halcott (1846-1895), regarding the procurement of current carte de visites of the publisher Thurlow Weed (1797-1892) and former New York Governor Horatio Seymour (1810-1886) for illustrations.
  - Neagle, John, circa 1825-1843; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
    John Neagle, ca. 1825-1827, to the theater manager Francis Courtney Wemyss (1797-1859), Philadelphia, regarding Neagle's busy schedule, his portrait in progress of the actor William Macready (PAFA), that years' exhibition at the PAFA, his portrait of the actor Junius Brutus Booth (Museum of the City of New York), and that he cannot undertake Wemyss's portrait anywhere but in his own studio.
    John Neagle, 25 September 1826, to the publisher Mathew Carey (1760-1839), Philadelphia, regarding compiling a list of names and addresses which includes the painter Thomas Sully, the engravers Gideon Fairman, Peter Maverick, James B. Longacre, and Hugh Bridport.
    John Neagle, 24 January 1827, to the publisher Mathew Carey (1760-1839), Philadelphia, regarding the amicable settlement of a dispute through arbitration, and mentions Joseph Hopkinson (1770-1842), President of the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, and the painter Thomas Sully.
    John Neagle, 26 March 1827, to the publisher Mathew Carey (1760-1839), Philadelphia, regarding Neagle requests the prominent publisher, who has made a solicitation to the artist, what the cost of a church pew will be.
    John Neagle, 9 June 1830, to the publisher Mathew Carey (1760-1839), Philadelphia, regarding Carey's, a prominent Irish Catholic, "Society for bettering the condition of the Roman Catholics" and Neagle's desire to become a member.
    John Neagle, 22 July 1843, to Joseph H. Hedges, Philadelphia, regarding acquiring an autograph of Washington Allston, to which Neagle directs him to either of the painters Thomas Sully or Samuel Finley Breese Morse.
  - Nicoll, James Craig, 1893; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Letter from J[ames] C[raig] Nicoll to "Mr. Skinner," 1893 May 29.
  - Nutting, Wallace, 1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Wallace Nutting clipped letter fragment, June 1938.
  - Palmer, Erastus Dow, 1893; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Erastus Dow Palmer, Albany, 18 December 1893, to the sculptor Jonathan Scott Hartley (1845-1912), New York, regarding his affection for his former pupil, the present of a carte de visite of the White Captive, mentions Daniel Chester French (1850-1931), John Quincy Adams Ward (1830-1910), Augustus Saint-Gaudens (1848-1907), and George Inness (1825-14). Includes photograph of the White Captive.
  - Peale, Rembrandt, 1852; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Rembrandt Peale (1778-1860), Philadelphia, 3 December 1852, to Mr. Drake. Re: responds that he would be delighted to provide three of his portraits of Washington to Mr. Drake's directors, as he already has two commenced. He recently sold one to "an English Gentleman, Mr. Tarret of Wolverhampton."
  - Peale, Rubens, 1837; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Autograph letter to Honorable M. Dikerson, Secretary of the Navy, signed "Rubens Peale." New York, 6 June 1837.
  - Pennell, Elizabeth Robins, 1920; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Elizabeth Robins Pennell (1855-1936), Philadelphia, 22 December 1920, to Violet Oakley (1874-1961). Re: Pennell accepts Oakley's invitation for her and her husband Joseph Pennell (1957-1926) to spend Christmas Eve together.
  - Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, 1875; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8)
    James L. Claghorne (1817-84), president of PAFA, and John Sartain (1808-97), artist and secretary of PAFA, jointly issue and sign a check for payment of $500 to the Philadelphia firm of Frank Furness and George Hewitt, for architectural designs of their landmark building for the PAFA, considered Frank Furness's masterpiece, completed in 1876.
  - Rosenthal, Tobias, 1881; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Munich, 11 March 1881, to Francis Seligsberg. Four-page letter written in German with a watercolor sketch of two female artists holding portfolios, one calm and tidy, the other quite disheveled.
  - Sargent, John Singer, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 10)
    John Singer Sargent (1856-1925, London, undated, to "My dear Trower." Re: "I have always thought, just after leaving you, of my [illeg] debt, the East End spree." Presumably to either Henry Seymour Trower or his wife Juliet.
  - Sartain, Emily, 1897-1903; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Season ticket to an Exhibition of Works by the Late John Sartain at the Art Club of Philadelphia, 1897. Signed with the compliments of "Emily Sartain."
    Autograph letter to Miss Levy, signed "Emily Sartain." Philadelphia, 28 May 1903. Letterhead: Philadelphia School of Design for Women/ Broad & Masters Streets/ Miss Emily Sartain, Principal.
  - Sartain, John, 1897; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Autograph letter to Fred. M. Hopkins, signed "John Sartain." Philadelphia, 31 August 1897. Includes sketch for title page of Sartain's book Reminiscences of a Very Old Man.
  - Sartain, William, 1883-1885; 1914; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Autograph note signed "William Sartain." New York, 7 January 1914.
    New York, 4 October 1883 to S. Louise Phelps (1843/4-after 1920, painter and teacher born Ohio), East Orange, New Jersey. Sartain informs Phelps when his classes will begin, the costs associated, and mentions that his student Miss Cardozo will arrive soon.
    New York, 3 May 1884 to S. Louise Phelps, East Orange, New Jersey. Sartain quotes Lord Byron, from a letter written in Venice, 14 April 1817.
    New York, 23 February 1885 to S. Louise Phelps, East Orange, New Jersey. Sartain wishes Phelps to submit his name for non-resident membership in the Orange Art Association; her friend Mrs. Narland [?] is now working in Sartain's studio and wishes to be remembered.
    New York, 26 March 1885 to S. Louise Phelps, East Orange, New Jersey. Sartain regrets that he cannot instruct her class this summer but suggests she approach Hugh Bolton Jones (1848-1927) or his brother Francis Coates Jones (1857-1932).
    New York, undated photograph of a female portrait inscribed to S. Louise Phelps: "with Christian regards of I William Sartain." [This is possibly a portrait of Phelps.]
  - Sliger, Robert, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 14)
    Undated letter envelope from Robert Sliger addressed to himself.
  - Smillie, George Henry, 1882; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 15)
    George Henry Smillie (1840-1921), Marblehead Neck, Massachusetts, 24 September 1882, to Hattie Merrifield. With a calling card signed "James D. Smillie," (James David Smillie 1833-1909). Re: George H. Smillie informs Hattie Merrifield that he will return to New York the first week of October, and that he takes pupils at $30 a month, or has a class on Thursdays which will begin in the second week of October, whichever she prefers.
  - Stillman, William James and Marie Spartali Stillman, circa 1875; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 16)
    St. Helen's Cottage, Ventnor, Isle of Wight, England, July? 1875, to Katherine Hillard (1839-1915). Stillman apologizes that she cannot see Hillard because her husband, William James Stillman (1828-1901), wishes to go immediately to Dalmatia and she must close up their house on the Isle of Wight.
    Amerstone, England, 15 June 1875, to Miss Katherine Hillard. Stillman invites Hillard to visit them at their cottage on the Isle of Wight, says the couple are happy despite the loss of their son, John Ruskin Stillman (1862-75), known as "Russie."
  - Sully, Thomas, 1839; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 17)
    23 September 1839, to Mr. Herring, New York. Sully informs Herring that the Portrait of Col. Abert (John James Abert 1788- 1863) has been shipped to Washington, and that the bill of lading is in possession of John Trumbull (1756-1843). Sully requests that the Abert portrait be exhibited in Washington prior to being exhibited at the New York Institution. Sully is also waiting on a frame before forwarding Herring his picture of Musidora.
  - Tanner, Henry Ossawa, 1906; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Henry Ossawa Tanner, Martigues, France, 11 Febraury 1906, to Mr. Morris.
  - Thayer, Abbott Handerson, circa 1883-1894; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Dictated letter (handwritten) to Sadakichi Hartmann, signed in another hand "A. H.Thayer." Monadnock, New Hampshire, 23 April [no year given].
    Autograph letter to Clara A. May, signed "Abbott H. Thayer." Annotated at top in another hand "21 April 1894."
    Autograph letter to Mr. Koehler, signed "Abbott H. Thayer." Cornwall-on-Hudson, 12 May 1885.
    Autograph letter to Mr. Koehler, signed "Abbott H. Thayer." Cornwall-on-Hudson, 31 October 1883.
    Autograph postcard to Mr. Koehler, signed "A. H. Thayer." Cornwall-on-Hudson, 19 May 1885 [postmark]. Postcard bears letterhead of Magazine of Art-Cassell & Company, Limited.
    Autograph postcard to Mr. Koehler, signed "A. H. T." Postmarked 1886.
  - Tuckerman, Henry T., 1854-1859; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Henry T. Tuckerman, art critic, New York, 6 November 1854, to Benson J. Lossing (1813-1891), historian and art historian. Regarding Tuckerman's desire to obtain a copy of Lossing's profusely illustrated Pictorial Field Book of the Revolution (1851) and inquiring about his progress on Pictorial Field Book of the War of 1812 (1862).
    Henry T. Tuckerman, New York, 4 June 1859, to Benson J. Lossing (1813-1891). Regarding Tuckerman's refusal of an editorship, Lossing's Field Book, and a dispute with Mr. Putnam over the authorship of a Peale painting.
  - Turner, Charles Yardley, 1885; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 21)
    Charles Yardley Turner (1850-1919), New York, 6 April 1885, to Laura Maude Wachschlager. Re: Wachschlager was a young autograph collector and Turner writes: "I will be pleased to see you at my studio some Saturday afternoon between 2 and 5 P. M."
  - Valentine, Edward Virginius, 1877; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 22)
    Edward Virginius Valentine, Richmond, 12 March 1877, to Dr. James M. Minor, New York, regarding Minor's returning his bust of General Robert E. Lee to him in Richmond.
  - Volk, Stephen Arnold Douglas, 1881-1915; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 23)
    Stephen Arnold Douglas Volk (1881-1915), New York, 18 January 1881, to Marion Larrabee, Chicago.
    Volk, New York 8 May 1911, to Marion Volk, Center Lovell, Maine.
    Volk, New York, 26 October 1911, to Marion Volk, Center Lovell, Maine.
    Volk, New York, 20 May 1915, to Marion Volk, Center Lovell, Maine.
  - Walcutt, William, circa 1860s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 24)
    William Walcutt (1819-1882) carte de visite by Augustus Morand, Brooklyn, of the Ohio born painter and sculptor.
  - Weir, Julian Alden, 1891; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 25)
    Julian Alden Weir (1852-1919), Branchville, Connecticut, 26 July 1891, to "Dear Max," [Paris, France]. Re: Weir sends eight etchings including the Portrait of Dr. Weir, "which is $35, already having sold some." "I hope you have made many finds in the shape of fine etchings (& not girls!). I have put etching aside for the present & have some twenty canvases under way."
  - Wenzler, Henry Antonio, circa 1860s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 26)
    Wenzler (b. Denmark-d. 27 May 1871, Newport, RI) carte de visite by Maurice Stadtfeld, photographer, 711 Broadway, New York.
  - West, Benjamin, 1816; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 27)
    London, 27 February 1816, to Richard James Laurence. West requests the loan of two pictures for an apparent exhibition of "all the pictures painted by me within the last fifty years." The first, Faith and Hope (from Spenser's "Poems of the Fairy Queen"), depicts Laurence's mother and sister, and the second, Una and the Lion, is a portrait of Laurence's wife, nee Miss Hall (Wadsworth Athenaeum, Hartford).
  - White, Stanford, 1892-1895; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 28)
    Typed letter signed "White" on the imprinted stationery of McKim, Mead & White. Two separate pages, four total. New York, 16 November 1895. To Frederick William MacMonnies.
    Typed letter signed "Stanford White" with holograph additions and three-line holograph postscript, on the imprinted stationery of McKim, Mead & White. Two separate pages, four total. New York, 19 January 1892. To Frederick William MacMonnies.
    New York, 4 February 1895, to Frederick W. MacMonnies (1863-1937, sculptor). On McKim, Mead & White letterhead, White informs MacMonnies that Daniel Chester French (1850-1931) has just dropped out of a commission, and White recommends that MacMonnies accept the order for five large caryatides for the American Surety Building, on Broadway and Pine, which White confides would be "a very good potboiler.
    "New York, 9 December 1895, to Frederick W. MacMonnies. Re: White wishes MacMonnies to set his price for the Washington Arch groups.
  - Whittredge, Worthington, 1879; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 29)
    Worthington Whittredge, New York, 2 February 1879, to Andrew Varick Stout Anthony (1835-1906), American wood engraver.
    New York, 28 December 1868, to Samuel A. Coale Jr., St. Louis.Whittredge writes to Coale, a St. Louis merchant and arts patron, apologizing that the little picture Coale recently purchased, a scene in the Lebanon Valley, New York, was not ready to be shipped as a Christmas present to this wife, due to damage sustained to the frame, but it will arrive before New Year's day. He explains that since the price charged was well below cost, Coale will have to pay for the expense of the frame, as well as the boxing and shipping. The picture is a little dry in places, so Whittredge advises Coale to take it out of its frame and spread boiled linseed oil evenly over the surface, in preference to varnish, as the work is displayed under glass.